<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scarbrough spaw spagyrically anatomized by Geo. Tonstall ...</title>
            <author>Tonstall, George, b. 1616 or 17.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12632959</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12632959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64813</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62933)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 337:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scarbrough spaw spagyrically anatomized by Geo. Tonstall ...</title>
                  <author>Tonstall, George, b. 1616 or 17.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 13-63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verses are appended.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed Feb. 21, 1669. Roger L'Estrange"--P. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  England.</term>
               <term>Mineral waters --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Health resorts --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:64813:1"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 21. 1669.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64813:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SCARBRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH</hi> SPAW SPAGYRICALLY ANATOMIZED.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Geo. Tonſtall,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for the Author. MDCLXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64813:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64813:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Nulla roſa naſcitur ſine ſpinis.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DOctor <hi>Witty</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der complains, that Mr. <hi>Simpſon</hi> by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him the trouble of anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Book, <hi>hath interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his deſign of a Latine Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py upon the ſubject of this</hi> Spaw, <hi>which he thought ſhould have ſeen the light this year.</hi> I would not willingly hinder any good work; let this little there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:64813:3"/>that I have writ, but ſerve only as an Appendix to his third Volume, and I ſhall clothe it in like faſhion: far be it from me to eſpouſe the quarrel of either of them; I profeſs my ſelf a friend to both; for if I ſhould not walk uniformly betwixt Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s Library, and Mr. <hi>Simpſon</hi>'s Laboratory, I might ſuſpect my ſelf a lame Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Helmont</hi> I declare are the two great lights that rule in my Hemiſphere. <hi>Galen</hi>'s method of Phyſick may juſtly be named rational ſo far as he writes after the old man his Maſters Copy, I dare not ſpeak further for him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64813:3"/>
            <p>I hope in this Tract my writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is ſo candid, that it may be obſerv'd what I have ſaid is not <hi>ad perſonam,</hi> but <hi>ad rem.</hi> And that I have not concern'd my ſelf in any word which Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> has been pleas'd to ſay in his two Books, but only what was neceſſary to take notice of <hi>me defendendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is but one Poſition that I have affirm'd upon the whole ſubject; if it be daubed up with untemper'd Mortar, let who will pull it down; but if its founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be built upon mechanical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, it muſt ſtand firmer than <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillar: by the Proceſs that I have taken, the
<pb facs="tcp:64813:4"/>material principles which I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert to be in this <hi>Spaw</hi> are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to our ſenſes, theſe are infallible judges <hi>(poſitis omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus requiſitis)</hi> of their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s failure was, in that he left off where he ſhould have begun: after he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd what is moſt conſpicuous about the <hi>Spaw,</hi> and tryed that the Gall tinctured the water of a dark purple colour, contents himſelf with fair probabilities for affirming his five princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and then, <hi>pag. 15. leaves it to others to try Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and make what new diſcoveries they can.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64813:4"/>
            <p>What unexpected things hath Anatomy diſcovered in the body of man theſe late years? to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate a tittle from the honour of theſe happy improvements of knowledge, were to ſpeak againſt the light, and to bark againſt the Moon: yet why muſt the uſefulneſs of this noble Art be confined to the Animal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom only? The grounds of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomy in the vegetable and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Kingdom, laid down by <hi>Tachenius,</hi> doth neerly conduce to the diſcovery of the Nature, Cauſe, and Cure of diſeaſes, if I know any thing. The little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection that I have made of
<pb facs="tcp:64813:5"/>
               <hi>Scarbrough</hi>'s <hi>Diana,</hi> gives the cauſe why one crys, great is <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>S.</hi> and another at the ſame time decrys it as much: the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral account for this confuſed noiſe is, becauſe as the liquor is commendable, ſo the dregs are inſufferable: the Eſſence of it fit for the Cup of a Prince, the <hi>caput mortuum,</hi> which is Sand and Clay, fit for nothing but the Brick-layers Trowel. Hence it doth follow, that thoſe who are weak in their digeſtive facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſtrong in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributive, theſe may find good by drinking this Water, and no harm by the ſordid feces,
<pb facs="tcp:64813:5"/>due care being taken: but thoſe who are weak in both, will experience the contrary. To all thoſe that have a petrifying character ſeminated in them, I ſay of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul Ite, cito abite, nunquam redite.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64813:6"/>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64813:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SCARBRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH</hi> SPAW SPAGYRICALLY ANATOMIZED.</head>
            <p>BEfore I enter into this Diſcourſe, I am neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to remove an Objection, leſt I ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble on the Threſhold: Says my honoured Patient, Laſt Year you perſwaded me, that <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Water was to be preferred before <hi>Knaisbrough;</hi> this Year you are of a contrary opinion, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64813:7"/>therefore I know not how to truſt you. I anſwer, firſt <hi>excuſively,</hi> you may note hereby, that I am not <hi>pertinacious; conviction</hi> of an <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> will work in me <hi>converſion</hi> to the <hi>truth:</hi> Again, I did commend to you no worſe thing than that which I took my ſelf; 'twere to be wiſhed that all Phyſicians were bound with this Girdle. Secondly, <hi>directly,</hi> for your particular trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Gravel,</hi> and <hi>Stone in the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys,</hi> I did prefer the <hi>Nitre</hi> at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> before the <hi>Vitriol</hi> of <hi>Knais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough: Appello Coronam,</hi> if that be not a more noble principle than this; yet muſt it be underſtood on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>caeteris paribus.</hi> Here my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake was incurable, until I got op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to ſift <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water in the Fire, the beſt <hi>Microſcope</hi> could not have ſhown me what lay in the bowels of it, only <hi>Spagyrick Anatomy</hi> made the Dirt appear to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64813:7"/>open view. For ſatisfaction to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who may cenſure my <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring</hi> from <hi>Knaisbrough</hi> to riſe from <hi>wavering</hi> in opinion, take this plain Narrative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1666. the famous fortunate Chyrurgeon Mr. <hi>Thomas Holiard</hi> of <hi>London</hi> (may this man be bleſſed in his deed) cut me for the Stone, which weighed four Ounces and a half; Six weeks after, I was able to take Journey; the Doctor there (my friend) told me his doubt, that <hi>Vitrioline</hi> Waters were too ſharp for me to drink, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my green wound ſo lately healed: notwithſtanding I reſolv'd for <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> remembring Mr. <hi>Stones</hi> caſe which his Father related to me long ſince, which was this; after his Son was cut, a large Stone taken out of his Bladder, the wound did not perfectly heal, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he had all the help that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64813:8"/>
               <hi>London</hi> could afford) for about three Months time, at laſt Sir <hi>Theod. Mayrne</hi> did adviſe him to <hi>Knais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Water, he had not drunk it fifteen days till he was perfectly healed; for which great Cure done by it, he did frequent that <hi>Spaw</hi> for many years after: this Water I mixed with white Wine, which brought away by Urine abundance of mucous matter. <hi>Helmont</hi> the Prince of Reaſon ſets down the cauſe hereof in theſe words; <hi>ubi cuſtodes malè ſe habent, continuò plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant partem proprii alimenti quod ſibi aſſimilare debebat:</hi> I was glad to ſee that this <hi>Spaw</hi> cleanſed the Bladder from that glutenous ſtuff, which (if let alone) would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly have laid a foundation for another Stone. Sandy Gravel (which few or none are exempted from) falling amongſt it, and mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it, muſt in continuance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64813:8"/>gather to a hard ſubſtance, too great to paſs away. I wiſh all thoſe that ſhall receive like mercy with me, would uſe the like means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a relapſe of that formidable Diſeaſe the Stone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1667. I returned thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again, the ſeaſon proved wet, during which time, the <hi>Spaw</hi> prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very weak of the mineral, this diſcouraged me from drinking much of it: I then blamed the great Ditch about the Fountain, as the cauſe of impoveriſhing the <hi>Spaw</hi> of its principle, for I judge it was as rational to pare an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to peel the Bark off a Tree, and hereby not indemnifie them, as to cut away the ſurface of the earth about a mineral Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; ſtanding water abiding all Winter in theſe deep Trenches, by ſinking down through the ſoftned earth, makes paſſage into the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64813:9"/>of the <hi>Spaw;</hi> then every ſhowre of Rain in the Summer will find the ſame crevices and clifts to deſcend into it: If this may ſuffice to get this fault mended, I ſhall be glad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1668. being moſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to look well to my ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the threatnings of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſtemper, I viſited <hi>Scarbrough</hi> during mine abode there.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I took notice what Doctor <hi>Witty</hi> ſays, <hi>pag.</hi> 151. <hi>that after he had exhaled the water from the body of the minerals, it would not unite with other waters, but lie all at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom undiſſolved.</hi> By this trial of his, I was certain that in that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Minerals there muſt be other things containd than his 4 or 5 prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; for <hi>Allom, Nitre, Salt,</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> are amicable to water, and without any force diſſolvable in it, neither may it be ſuppoſed that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64813:9"/>the fire in exhaling the Water can alter the texture of Salts, ſo as to hinder their diſſolution; for the more Salts are calcined, the more ſpeedily do they imbibe the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as thirſting for it, as Ice doth, therefore eaſily melt in Water, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it proceeded from it, for the ſame reaſon Salts muſt do ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. If any one doubt of this, let him try the Lord <hi>Blay</hi>'s Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that learned Frenchman, <hi>viz.</hi> calcine Sea-Salt, deliquiate it, then diſtill all that will come over, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat this proceſs, and you will find that all the Salt is turned into Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as devoid of all ſaltneſs, as is diſtilled Rain Water.</p>
            <p>Next thing I obſerved was theſe words of his, <hi>pag.</hi> 13. <hi>Nor can the principles be ſeparated further than I have already expreſſed, namely, by putting Gall to the Water, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding many ingenious Gentlemen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64813:10"/>have endeavoured it:</hi> I wiſh thoſe he means had applied their wits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the uſefulneſs of Experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Philoſophy, as the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Boyle</hi> has done, and then their endeavours would have ſucceeded here, and to higher purpoſes than the ſeparating the principles of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw;</hi> where the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty lay that obſtructed the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I cannot apprehend, for <hi>fire</hi> alone is an inſtrument ſufficient to effect it. This <hi>ſubſtance</hi> (if I may ſo call it) being as ſubtile as the light, muſt penetrate through the <hi>centre</hi> of every <hi>pore</hi> of the mixed Water, and becauſe of its property to aſcend upward, it doth inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſquiet the <hi>lodge</hi> of <hi>heterogeneals:</hi> during this reſtleſs Motion, <hi>like</hi> things do <hi>occur</hi> with <hi>like,</hi> and their <hi>Nature</hi> is to <hi>unite:</hi> after this manner (as I conceive) it comes to paſs that <hi>ignis ſegregat heterogenea, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregat
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64813:10"/>homogenea:</hi> by no other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice did I extract out of the <hi>Spaw</hi> Water a pure <hi>nitroaluminous Salt,</hi> and a large quantity of <hi>feces</hi> apart, both which I then ſhewed to the Honourable Lord <hi>Faulconbridge,</hi> who can remember what I ſaid then to his Lordſhip of it. At this time I could not be certain but that much of the Sand which ſettled to the bottom in the Preparation, came through the careleſneſs of the Porter that brought me the Water, and therefore I could not come to a poſitive determination by this Experiment; only I wrote to Mr. <hi>Simpſon,</hi> wiſhing him to forbear publiſhing any thing concerning <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> till he had ſpoke with me, becauſe I had made a tryal what was contained in it; his anſwer was, my advice came too late, for his Book was in the Preſs, ſo far was I from having a hand in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64813:11"/>the framing his Book, as Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> was made to believe by the report of others.</p>
            <p>This Year 1669. I returned thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and though I dropt <hi>Oleum Salis</hi> tinctured with Gold in every other Glaſs, hoping thereby to cleanſe off the <hi>ſordes</hi> of the <hi>Spaw,</hi> yet after a fortnights drinking, it gave me a fit of the Stone, which from the time Mr. <hi>Holiard</hi> cured me, I had not felt before. I brought the Water home with me, that I might be ſure that nothing extrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>Spaw</hi> might interrupt a <hi>critical Analyſis</hi> thereof; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct confirmed my firſt Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I made at <hi>Scarbrough;</hi> all the materials that can be found in it, are three, firſt <hi>Raments</hi> of Stone, ſecondly a <hi>Nitroalumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous</hi> Salt, and thirdly, a <hi>gleeb</hi> of <hi>Allom:</hi> their proportions are thus, of the <hi>Stone-powder,</hi> one Ounce
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64813:11"/>and three Drams; of the <hi>Nitroalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous Salt,</hi> one Ounce and ſix Drams; of the <hi>Blew-Clay,</hi> which is the <hi>gleeb</hi> of <hi>Allom,</hi> three Drams; the <hi>active principles,</hi> and the <hi>caput mortuum</hi> are equal; ſo that if Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s tryal be true, that five Quarts of Water give one Ounce of the body of Mineral (as he calls it) you take half an Ounce of Stone and Clay into your Bowels, every ſuch quantity you drink.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee a cauſe (as I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved before) why this Body of Minerals would not diſſolve in Water, namely, the Stone and Clay by the heat of the Fire (while he exhal'd the Water dry from them) become more compacted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Salts, than when they were in the Fountain; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as when theſe Salts are ſeparated from their droſs, they melt as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily as Snow in Water.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64813:12"/>
            <p>You will ſay, how comes it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, that there is ſo much Filth in <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water, as you ſpeak of? For anſwer, take notice, Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> tells you, that the <hi>Spaw,</hi> which is a quick Spring, cometh out at the foot of an exceeding high Clift, all the Stone and Earth that maketh up this Mountain is big belly'd with <hi>Nitre, Allom-Stone</hi> here and there mingled in it; after the Spring has run through this high Hill, the <hi>Spaw</hi> is brought forth, which is fair and clear to look to; I cannot but compare it to an Harlot, of whom it is ſaid, She eateth and wipeth her mouth, and ſaith, I have done no wickedneſs. This hungry <hi>eſurine</hi> Water, after ſhe has devoured Stone in a large quantity, as if that were not ſufficient for to grate her Teeth upon, ſhe hath ſwallowed both Cup and Liquor of the Allom. Becauſe I have dealt with her, as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64813:12"/>
               <hi>Aeſop</hi> dealt with the Boy that had eaten the Figs, made her vomit them up again; whoſoever is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with me for doing ſo, I muſt bear it. If any of her friends think I do bely her, let them for their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction firſt anſwer this Query.</p>
            <p>From what cauſe is it, after you have drunk a Month of it, then, if not before, it takes a Reſty, <hi>Jadiſh fit,</hi> will neither go backward nor forward? A Noble Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to me that the Water dealt thus with him: his Lordſhip ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drunk it with ſucceſs about a Month, it then ſwell'd him at ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack two or three laſt days, and would neither work by Urine nor Stool, though he took his uſual Phyſick with it, as formerly, the Scotch Pill, which is an Extract of Aloes: I advis'd him to take one Dram and half of the pure Eſſence with the <hi>Spaw</hi> Water; by the help
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64813:13"/>of this, and the ſaid Pill, he had plentiful Evacuations in that After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon: thus being quitted of his oppreſſion, he meddled no farther with the Water. This Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> hath carefully obſerved, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adviſeth thus, <hi>pag.</hi> 211.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man finds, that after bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit once had by the Waters, he begins to decline again in his health, as that his appetite or concoction decay, or the Waters paſs not ſo well as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but cauſe diſtention, either in the Belly or the Veins, and ſo bring on a difficulty of breathing, or pain in the head, or the like, it is then time wholly to deſiſt, and to proceed no farther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is honeſtly ſpoken, but is this the manner of other Waters, when they are fitly ſuited to a Chronical Diſtemper, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient find once benefit by them, do they produce in him afterwards
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64813:13"/>ſuch evils as theſe? or rather, the longer they are drunk till the Cure be wrought, the nearer the Patient is carried to his deſired end. Is there not therefore a ſting in the tail of <hi>Scarbrough</hi>-Water? are not the <hi>Stone-feces plaiſtered</hi> upon the inner Coat of the Bowels, diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>periſtaltick</hi> Motion, and obſtructing the <hi>attraction</hi> of the <hi>lacteal</hi> Veins, the cauſe of all thoſe evils?</p>
            <p>This Query thus anſwered, for further ſatisfaction proceed after this manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Take a large quantity of the clear <hi>Spaw</hi> Water, in caſe you fear any Sand may be taken up with it, put all through a Woolen Cloth, boil it till half be conſumed, clear off that Liquor, then ſee how much Sand you find at the bottom; which is nothing elſe but part of the ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64813:14"/>Rock, which the Water has diſſolv'd, exhale that Liquor low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the thickneſs of Oyl, then pour it forth into a wooden Veſſel; ſet it by in the cold, and the <hi>Nitre</hi> and <hi>Allom</hi> ſettles into <hi>cryſtals:</hi> when that Liquor will caſt forth no more of theſe, then exhale the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor dry, put Water to it, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and you will find more <hi>Stone-Powder</hi> in the Paper; exhale this Water perfectly dry, then burn it in a Crucible, diſſolve it with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and filter it, there will you have the <hi>blew Clay;</hi> which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the <hi>gleeb</hi> of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom:</hi> If you pleaſe to proceed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, diſſolve the firſt <hi>Cryſtals, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale,</hi> and <hi>filter,</hi> ſo often till the <hi>Cryſtals</hi> be pure and white, ſo will be ſeparated more <hi>ſandy Clay.</hi> By all this that I have ſaid and proved to thoſe that will truſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64813:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>their own eyes, I affirm this as my Poſition <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Nature of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> is petrifying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall prove it by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (which to Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar omnium</hi>) of <hi>Kircher, lib.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 46. <hi>Quaeritur quid propriè ſit ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus lapidificus; dico eſſe Saxum nitro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, aquâ eliquat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> his whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>de Origine Succi petrifici,</hi> doth make manifeſt this truth, as if it were written with the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by Experiment, I made it viſible that the <hi>Spaw</hi> is moſtly nothing elſe, but the <hi>nitrous</hi> Stone melted in Water, beſides the <hi>Allom-ſtone</hi> that is imbibed in it; There is a famous petrifying Water at the Bridge-end of <hi>Knaisbrough</hi> Weſt-ward, known by the name
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64813:15"/>of <hi>Dropping-well,</hi> a <hi>Stillicidium</hi> of a <hi>nitrous</hi> Rock. I ſent for a Quart of this Water (which was very clear) and diſtill'd it in a <hi>Glaſs Retort,</hi> which gave a Dram, want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ten Grains) of pure white <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre</hi> and <hi>Stone:</hi> by this 'tis obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Allom</hi> juice joined with the <hi>Nitre,</hi> has corroded and imbibed more Stone than this notorious <hi>petrifying</hi> Water at <hi>Knaisbrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would not be here miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as if I did from hence infer, that <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying than this Water, which will ſet a ſtony Cruſt upon a Loaf, or piece of Wood, after it has lain in it a few hours: this manifeſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of petrifaction <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not charged with. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the difference I apprehend to be thus, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>alkali</hi> of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> in <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water hath in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64813:15"/>part imbib'd the acidity of the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, and therefore it cannot ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate the Wood put in it, as to leave a cruſt of Stone upon its ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies, which the other Water having Nitre alone in it will do. That <hi>Allom</hi> is an Alkali Salt, is plain from its ſaponary property, this the Dyers have experienced: Again, when <hi>Allom</hi> is put in a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible over the fire, it burns to a light porous Cinder, <hi>Vacua eſſe alcalium corpora demonſtravit Tachenius.</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre on the contrary doth flux in the Fire into a hard compact body, whereby it is evident, that in Nitre the acid hath the predominium, in Allom the Alcali; and therefore <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water cannot manifeſt its petrifying property by putting Wood into it, and cruſting it over as the other Water doth: yet he that will affirm, that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water hath no ſuch occult quality
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64813:16"/>in it, muſt firſt prove that it carries no Stone Powder in the Bowels of it; which is manifeſtly falſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By the <hi>Aporrhoea Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus lapidifici,</hi> there are found on the Clift neer the <hi>Spaw,</hi> Muſcle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhells, and ſuch like things petrified to a ſtony ſubſtance; one of theſe was ſhown to Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> this year, but he accuſed the Sea for petrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; if ſo, what befel <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife <hi>judicially,</hi> is not ſo great a miracle, as that it is not our <hi>lot</hi> naturally to be turned into <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Salt,</hi> that eat ſo much of <hi>Sea-Salt</hi> daily; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when the Earth of the Cliff falleth down by daſhes of Rain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sands, as ſoon as the watery moiſture is exhaled from it, it doth petrifie. Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> tells you of a lump of Earth thus petrified that will load two Carts, which becauſe it was of a rediſh Colour, and hard, he miſtook it for Iron.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64813:16"/>
            <p>Fourthly, by the effects the <hi>Spaw</hi> produceth, primarily in thoſe that are inclinable to the Stone: I wiſh <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> had given me no juſt occaſion to complain of it in this particular; beſides what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to me there, (as I ſaid) I was no ſooner come home from thence, but another ſharp fit tormented me for two days; that I am not alone in this accuſation, may be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s Book; if ſuch complainings as theſe had not been vulgarly ſpoken, I ſuppoſe, ſo wiſe a man as he would not have ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Objection againſt the <hi>Spaw, pag.</hi> 150. <hi>Another</hi> (ſays he) <hi>never had a ſit of the Stone till drinking of theſe Waters, though few of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily have eſcaped that Diſeaſe:</hi> is not this a ſhrewd ſign of its <hi>petrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> nature? his <hi>Parentheſis</hi> doth not invalidate it, for, <hi>multae ſunt in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, quae nunquàm reducuntur in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64813:17"/>actum;</hi> but take his anſwer to this Objection; <hi>Even juſt ſo a Light is brought into a dark Room, by which a Thief is diſcovered, therefore Light is ill for a Thief; by the ſame conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that</hi> Scarbrough Spaw <hi>is ill for the Stone.</hi> An Objection of this weight muſt not be anſwered ſo lightly, we that have been afflicted with this Diſtemper cannot be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with ginglings when they tend to our miſchief: But to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, The Thief is in the <hi>Spaw,</hi> the Water was not ſuch a dark Room where the Thief has lain hid ſo long, but if a Light had been brought in by a Chymiſt, this Thief might have been diſcovered before this time, and then <hi>Nephri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> men would have been aware of it. I grant, by reaſon of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>Nitre</hi> in the Water, it will force out ſtony Gravel in the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, when any is there; but I am
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64813:17"/>certain alſo becauſe, of the plenty of <hi>Stone filings</hi> that are in it, the Water will occaſion the <hi>breeding</hi> of Stones in the Kidneys, where, <hi>pro tempore;</hi> there are none; ask thoſe that have quitted themſelves of the Stones they voided by drinking the Water, if after they returned home, fits have not come on them more frequently and ſharply than before they drank of <hi>Scarbrough-Spaw.</hi> I proteſt to the world, both as to my ſelf, Relations, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, I have found it ſo: to ſhew the diſſerence betwixt <hi>Scarbrough</hi> and <hi>Knaisbrough</hi> Water (as to this petrifying property) I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a remarkable Obſervation of Mr. <hi>Henry Proctor</hi> of <hi>Farnly,</hi> I had the relation of it from his own mouth when we were together; this Gentleman was brought very low in an Hectick Fever, and ſadly troubled with ſhortneſs of breath,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64813:18"/>he conſulted with Dr. <hi>Henry Poor</hi> for Cure, but found no Remedy; he then applied himſelf to Dr. <hi>Neal,</hi> who prepared his body, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him to drink <hi>Knaisbrough</hi> Water, which cauſed him cough up <hi>ſeveral Stones</hi> daily till he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured. He does enjoy his health very well ever ſince, uſing thoſe Waters once a year; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he married, and now is Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of two Children; if this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient had been ſent to <hi>Scarbrough-Spaw,</hi> what had become of him let others judge; as the Diſeaſe of the Stone doth immediately proceed from a <hi>petriſick ſpirit,</hi> the cauſe <hi>ſine quâ non,</hi> ſo <hi>Jaundiſe</hi> and the <hi>Gout</hi> have their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from it, hence it doth follow, that, <hi>ſecondarily</hi> theſe two <hi>Diſtempers</hi> are dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly <hi>exalted</hi> (in bodies that are inclinable to them) by drinking this <hi>Spaw:</hi> for evidence of this
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64813:18"/>truth, I ſhall give inſtances: Firſt, the Lord <hi>Erwin</hi> went from his Houſe at <hi>Temple-Newſam</hi> to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> (upon what other account than to divert himſelf there with the company of his friends, I know not) after he had drunk the Water, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home, preſently the <hi>Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi> ſeizes on him, of which Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe he ſhortly died, though Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> uſed all means for his reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; now this I ſay, all <hi>ſweet Spaws</hi> in the World have a property com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them, that they are of a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opilating</hi> nature, and though they may not ſuit to every Diſeaſe, yet for the removing of grand <hi>Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> (the cauſe of moſt Diſeaſes) they are generally the <hi>beſt,</hi> and moſtly the <hi>laſt</hi> advice of all <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> what reaſon then can be given why this Honourable <hi>Lord</hi> by drinking <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> Water had not the <hi>Obſtructions</hi> of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64813:19"/>his Gall opened, but contrarily brought into this irrecoverable Diſeaſe that kill'd him? I ſay what reaſon elſe, if not this, <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water did <hi>petrifie</hi> that <hi>Sulphurous Saline</hi> humour in the <hi>Veſica bilaria</hi> into Stones, too great to paſs through the <hi>porus?</hi> Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> blamed his too liberal drinking of wine with it (as he ſaid to my ſelf this year) but what harm could that do more than to increaſe Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, which humour unpetrified is moſt eaſily purged away of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? That Stones do as uſually concrete in the <hi>Gall,</hi> as in the <hi>Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys,</hi> in men as well as in beaſts, who doth queſtion? I was preſent many years ſince at a <hi>Phyſick Lecture</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> when the Profeſſor in the Diſcourſe of the <hi>Jaundiſe</hi> brought forth three or four little <hi>Stones</hi> of <hi>Gall</hi> wrapt up in his Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchif, to ſhew them to the other
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64813:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Doctors there, relating that a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> afflicted with that Diſeaſe, after many fruitleſs attempts made by him for her Cure, at laſt was put to it to give her a Doſe of ſharp working Phyſick, which quitted her of thoſe Stones, whereby ſhe forthwith recovered: if any object, that ſuppoſe the <hi>Gall</hi> be petrified, yet it cannot cauſe death in ſo ſhort a time as this Lord took his Diſeaſe, and died in it.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, let him conſult <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> with <hi>Syloius,</hi> and there is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſatisfie him, that the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond fermentation</hi> made by the <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus pancreaticus,</hi> and the <hi>Gall,</hi> are as neceſſary for the preſervation of life, as the <hi>firſt fermentation</hi> is, that's in the <hi>Stomack;</hi> though in an Oxe Gall there is often found a great Stone, notwithſtanding the beaſt keeps health and liking till the Butcher ſlaughter him, yet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64813:20"/>then there is abundance of liquid choler beſides in his <hi>Veſica bilaria,</hi> ſufficient to perform <hi>fermentation;</hi> I ſhall mention but two other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this year in our Town. An <hi>Alderman</hi> whoſe Father ſome years ſince died of the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> but himſelf was never troubled with it, till after his coming from <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water, then did the <hi>Symptoms</hi> of this Diſeaſe appear, only it did not manifeſt it ſelf ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine,</hi> or by <hi>Colour</hi> of his body, which gave me a great cauſe of ſuſpicion that the water had <hi>petrified</hi> the <hi>Gall;</hi> with <hi>Chalibeat,</hi> and other <hi>Icterical</hi> drinks, by ſlow degrees he recovered.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Merchant</hi>'s Wife with Child, for company of her Husband, came to <hi>Scarbrough:</hi> Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> in his Book approving the Water ſafe for ſuch, ſhe deſired to drink of it, upon her return home, a tormenting
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64813:20"/>pain ſeized on her right ſide, for mitigation of this extream dolour, and prevention of a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> was thrice or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, then an <hi>Antimonial</hi> Vomit, yet ſo obdurated was the Gall, by the <hi>petrifying</hi> property of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Water, as I ſuſpected, that none other ſign appeared of the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> but a return of her pain three or four times over, at length a <hi>ternary ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Wine, Nitre,</hi> and <hi>Mercury elixerated</hi> diſſolved the congealed Choler, and then did the Diſeaſe ſhine forth in its <hi>ſaffron</hi> colour; after <hi>three recidivations</hi> ſhe was pluckt out of the Jaws of death, beyond the hopes of all her friends, and is now well deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a <hi>luſty Boy:</hi> Let it be here obſerved that I practiſe according to conſcience, and let thoſe She-Tatlers, who when they have done mumbling over their Beads, come
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64813:21"/>to a Feaſt, and there mutter hard ſpeeches againſt me for dealing ſo ſeverely with this Patient, take notice that it is my principle, when I ſee my duty, to purſue it to the <hi>hazard</hi> of my <hi>credit</hi> with ſuch as them: and though I be ſingular in this point from the moſt of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whoſe wiſdom it is to ſecure themſelves from an evil report, by doing <hi>nothing</hi> in a <hi>doubtful</hi> caſe; yet I have not ſo <hi>learned</hi> Chriſt. The Maxim is true, <hi>quod unicum eſt, non deliberandum eſt,</hi> and the reſolution is Chriſtian, <hi>Let us quit our ſelves like men</hi> of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity,</hi> and let <hi>the Lord do what ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him good.</hi> Pardon this digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Reader.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> gives an inſtance, <hi>pag.</hi> 180. of a Knight and his Lady in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> by drinking the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at home for the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> both of them took the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64813:21"/>they recovered not from, till <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> following; he blames the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of place from the Fountain for this fault of the Water; but all that can be charged upon drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a diſtance, is, that it may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the good, and increaſe the bad qualities of the Water which are innate.</p>
            <p>The Gouts inveterate malice is known to ariſe from a <hi>petrifying</hi> property of its <hi>acid Spirit,</hi> hence 'tis ſaid, <hi>Tollere nodoſam, neſcit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicina podagram.</hi> If loſers may have leave to ſpeak, I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water dealt with me as to this Diſtemper, which all my life long I never felt the leaſt touch on before: no ſooner was an uſual Stone ſlipped into the Bladder, from the left Kidney (of which I have ſpoke) but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <hi>ictu oculi,</hi> a Thunder-bolt from the right Kidney darted into
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64813:22"/>the joint of the great Toe, which cauſed me to go limping a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night after: Thus have my Reins tryed what is that water of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough Spaw.</hi> That I am not alone neither in this accuſation, hear Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> pag. 149. <hi>Others drinking without due preparation as was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary (peradventure to ſave ſome petty charge) have fallen into the Gout, the water contracting heat for want of ſpeedy paſſage, being thrown by nature upon the weak Joints, have hence inferred that theſe Waters cauſe the Gout.</hi> Anſwer, Theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men without peradventure may be ſuppoſed to have neglected that which is judged neceſſary for them to do before they drink Water, yet I do aver, no <hi>Spaw</hi> in the world has leſs need of preparatives, and more need of Purgers than this of <hi>Scarbrough:</hi> it was never obſerved by me, that any at the firſt morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64813:22"/>draught of this Water, wanted a ſpeedy paſſage by the back door. Though I cannot approve of his Notion touching the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, how and wherefore the water cauſeth the Gout, yet in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it does ſo in Bodies inclinable to that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, we are both agreed. Thus having proved by all manner of Arguments both <hi>à priori</hi> and <hi>à po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriori,</hi> that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water is <hi>petrifying,</hi> and have manifeſted that <hi>Knaisbrough Spaw</hi> (which partakes of the Vitriol of Iron) by a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Inſtance is quite otherwiſe; it now remains, only that I make out <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water has no Vitrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Spirit in it. In this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, I ſhall approve my ſelf a greater friend to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> than Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> who maintains the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for if in this water the <hi>eſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> Spirit of <hi>Vitriol</hi> be joined with the <hi>Volatile</hi> Spirit of <hi>Nitre,</hi> of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64813:23"/>which this <hi>Spaw</hi> doth chiefly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take; how then doth it differ from <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> that deadly <hi>corroſive</hi> water, which is nothing elſe, but theſe two <hi>acid ſpirits</hi> inſeparably united together? if he ſay theſe two are not all, there is Allom and Salt alſo, this makes the Water worſe, for a Spirit from all theſe will make an <hi>Aqua Regia,</hi> which doth corrode <hi>Gold</hi> it ſelf, the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all Metals to diſſolve. If it be ſaid theſe <hi>corroſive</hi> Spirits are <hi>extorted</hi> by <hi>ſtreſs</hi> of <hi>fire</hi> from their bodies, which extraordinary heat will not be granted to be in the bowels of the Earth. I anſwer, this poſſibly may excuſe <hi>à tanto,</hi> but not <hi>à toto:</hi> for firſt, the prolifick Seminals of all things generated in the Earth, doth come to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>matrixes</hi> in a vapour. If any queſtion this, let him try <hi>Platt</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, put <hi>bituminous</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64813:23"/>ſubſtances into two Glaſs <hi>Retorts,</hi> filling their necks, the one with <hi>lean Earth,</hi> the other with <hi>peet-earth,</hi> ſet them in an open <hi>fire,</hi> and by gradual heat the Vapours that aſcend will <hi>petrifie,</hi> the one Earth into <hi>Stone,</hi> and the other Earth into a <hi>plain coal.</hi> Secondly, this Vapour, if it be of ill quality, hath the ſame pernicious <hi>effects</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our bodies, as thoſe that are <hi>ſublimed</hi> by <hi>Art</hi> in the <hi>fire.</hi> This truth the Miners do ſadly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the <hi>Sulphurous</hi> Vapours that are in every <hi>Coal-pit,</hi> will ſoon <hi>ſtifle</hi> any that goes into it before it be purged by air conveyed to it. Thirdly, this Vapour Nature can no more cauſe to aſcend upward (which it doth perpetually) without heat, than <hi>Art</hi> can <hi>ſublime</hi> without <hi>fire. Suppono</hi> (ſays <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher) omnes vapores nihil aliud quàm tenuiſſima, ſubtiliſſima ac
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64813:24"/>inſenſibilia corpuſcula eſſe, quae calore exaltata ingentis in terreno mundo mutationis cauſa ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, I ſay, though we know that <hi>Nitre</hi> and <hi>Vitriol</hi> diſtill'd <hi>diviſim,</hi> are both of them ſeverally good, and of daily practice; yet we experience alſo, that diſtill'd <hi>conjunctim,</hi> they ſend forth the moſt deadly <hi>corroſive Vapour,</hi> which by the coldneſs of the Receiver is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſed to a Spirit; there can be no doubt, but if both theſe (as Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> would have it) be joined in <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water, it muſt be highly corroſive, though not to ſuch a degree as <hi>Aqua Fortis</hi> is, twenty drops whereof will kill a Cat; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I ſhall examine his proofs for this Vitriol of Iron, as I find them in his Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. he ſays, <hi>a ſmall quantity of Gall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put into the Spaw Water, doth turn it into a dark Claret Colour,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:64813:24"/>ergo, <hi>there is Vitriol in it;</hi> this is a <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> for thus will the Gall turn a Coal-water, if it has gotten any touch of the <hi>Spirit of Sulphur</hi> to ſharpen it, for diſſolution of the black Mine that it paſſeth through: but we will ſuppoſe there is no Coal-Mine about <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſay, it is only the <hi>Allom-Stone</hi> in the <hi>Spaw</hi> that gives the <hi>tincture</hi> by the <hi>Gall;</hi> let experience prove it, take any <hi>Allom-ſtone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurnt,</hi> powder it, adde Spring-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſharpened with the Spirit of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre</hi> that it may diſſolve it, and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, ſo will you have (to appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) a water as clear as the <hi>Spaw,</hi> put Powder of <hi>Gall</hi> thereto, and it gives you the ſame <hi>tincture.</hi> I am witneſs that the <hi>Chymical</hi> Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary of <hi>York</hi> did pick out of the Hill near the <hi>Spaw,</hi> an <hi>Allom-ſtone</hi> that was not hardened in the air, but made ſoft in the <hi>Nitre</hi> which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64813:25"/>abounds there, and after he mixed only Spring water with it, and added the Gall to it, it gave as high a <hi>Claret colour,</hi> as the <hi>Spaw</hi> it ſelf doth.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon of theſe Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is plainly thus; the <hi>acid</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſſolves the black <hi>Coal,</hi> or the blew <hi>Stone,</hi> and hides the colour of them in its pores, becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Atome of the <hi>continens</hi> muſt be <hi>outward</hi> to the <hi>contentum.</hi> The Gall being put in and ſtirred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt it, by its <hi>Alcaly</hi> imbibing the <hi>acidity</hi> of the water, what is included therein is <hi>extruded</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the bottom, where, what is precipitated appears in its own co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, the Spirit of <hi>Salts</hi> adding luſtre thereto.</p>
            <p>I will not mention here, how Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> commends this black ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment for Phyſical uſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. Againſt this Experiment of <hi>Allom</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64813:25"/>Stone giving its tincture by the Gall, let be obſerved how Dr. <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> miſtakes in his tryals; ſays he in his anſwer to Mr. <hi>Simpſon, pag.</hi> 91. <hi>I have tryed the Allom Mine, having broken it to powder, and infuſed it in Spring water ſome hours, and it received no tincture from the Gall.</hi> Good reaſon, for he did but <hi>infuſe</hi> it, not <hi>diſſolve</hi> it; can it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that the Gall ſhould preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate the Allom Stone from the water, whilſt it came not into it, but only lay at the bottom undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd? what can ſimple water ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract out of a hard Slate? no more than a Feather can ſtrike fire out of a Flint Stone: Nay more (ſaith he) <hi>I calcin'd that very Stone, and then diſſolved it in</hi> Spring water, <hi>and yet it received no tincture from the Gall.</hi> Anſwer. No marvel nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the calcin'd Stone of Allom is white; its blewneſs, which
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64813:26"/>gives the <hi>tincture,</hi> diſappears by the <hi>ſire;</hi> even as <hi>red</hi> Coral calcin'd in a Crucible turns white of Colour. Further, to let the Reader know that he will ſpare for no pains to give ſatisfaction, <hi>pag.</hi> 92. he <hi>ſends to two ingenious Gentlemen at</hi> Whitby, <hi>where is a water that breaks out of the middle of a Mine, to try if that would receive tincture from Gall, and they did both aſſure him it did not; beſides they ſent a Glaſs-bottle of the ſame water to</hi> York, <hi>where he tryed it himſelf, and it did not change at all.</hi> Why? what's the matter? he is anſwered out of his own mouth, <hi>Nay,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I do aver with them that it is like ordinary Spring-water,</hi> (in truth it is none other, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers drink of it, to quench their thirſt) <hi>having taken no vapour, odour, or Sapour from the Mine;</hi> yet he doth confidently conclude from this tryal that it is not from Allom
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64813:26"/>that this Water at <hi>Scarbrough</hi> takes its incture. Such another Errand as this to <hi>Whitby,</hi> he makes to <hi>Barn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley</hi> upon the edge of <hi>Darby-ſhire,</hi> to try if a Spring of freſh Water that runs out of <hi>Iron-ſtone,</hi> would change colour with Gall: and it did not, neither there, nor at <hi>York.</hi> What can be inferred from hence, but that this Water which ran from the Iron-ſtone was no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with the Iron, than that at <hi>Whitby</hi> was with the Allom; nay, <hi>à potiori,</hi> if a Mineral Salt of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom whiles crude, and imbodied in its Gleeb, doth not always im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to the Spring that runs through it, either Odour, Sapour, or Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, as he hath ſaid before, much leſs will the Metal of Iron-ſtone do it. If his friend that for a further tryal made a hole in the bottom Stone, to ſee if the Water that ſtood in it would tinge by Gall,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64813:27"/>had ſent him a Bottle of any Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that came from the Iron-ſtone, whilſt it was in <hi>ſolutis principiis,</hi> I do affirm that Water would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive tincture from Gall; ſuch a Water we have at <hi>Hunwick,</hi> where great quantity of Iron-ſtone is dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged up, and it receives tincture from Gall as highly as <hi>Scarbrough</hi> doth. Dr. <hi>Witty, pag.</hi> 94. is fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Argument <hi>ab inductione</hi> thus. <hi>The tincture by Gall is not from Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, nor from Iron,</hi> ergo, <hi>'tis from Vitriol:</hi> Anſwer, I am loth to ſee my Brother in the pinfold, yet muſt I ſay, if it be from the Vitriol, it is becauſe of the Iron that is in it, for no other Vitriol but <hi>ferrugineum</hi> will do it: hence it will follow, if not from Iron, then 'tis not from Vitriol, <hi>ergo,</hi> 'tis from Allom that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water tinges by Gall.</p>
            <p>His ſecond proof, <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Anderton</hi> obſerved that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64813:27"/>the Water carried in an Oaken Veſſel, in the bottom whereof was found a <hi>yellowiſh</hi> ſediment, which he ſent to the Doctor, he ſaw it like <hi>crocus Martis,</hi> and taſted it of a <hi>ſtiptick</hi> quality, and therefore 'tis ſuppoſed by him to be the <hi>Chalybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate</hi> part of the Minerals. Anſwer, <hi>Quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> volumus, facilè credimus.</hi> The ſharp Water agitated againſt the Oaken Veſſel, in carrying <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodes</hi> the inner <hi>parts</hi> of it, which powder ſetling to the bottom, with ſome <hi>ſeces</hi> of the <hi>Spaw</hi> Water pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth a ſettlement of the colour of Oak, which if he had dried, and then burnt in a Crucible, the flame thereof would have ſhown him, that it was <hi>Wood</hi> and not <hi>Iron.</hi> If different things were not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times like one another, none could be deceived. <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. <hi>The water at</hi> 40 <hi>Miles diſtance will not cruddle Milk as it doth at</hi> Scarbrough, <hi>and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64813:28"/>that it doth not receive ſuch a deep tincture from the Gall, nor is it found to have ſuch a pleaſant acidity as at the Fountain: which certainly muſt proceed from a loſs of the Vitrioline Spirits, of which it doth eminently participate.</hi> Anſwer, Who queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that Allom will not cruddle Milk as well as Vitriol? the more ſubtile any acid Liquor put to Milk is, the more perfectly doth it ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the thick parts from the thin; 'twill follow therefore that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath loſt ſome of its ſubtile Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, by carrying, but none of the Vitriol which it never had. The tincture from the Gall I have mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to proceed from the Unburnt Allom Stone, whereof this is a plain proof; put the <hi>Spaw</hi> Water into Glaſs Bottles at the Fountain, let them be carried abroad and left a few days, and the Allom Stone will ſettle of it ſelf without any
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64813:28"/>mixture of Gall, to the bottom, in a blackiſh Powder, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any thing of <hi>Chalybs,</hi> for two Reaſons; Firſt, becauſe the <hi>Vitrioline</hi> Spirit, and Iron are too great friends (being once met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) to be ſo eaſily ſeparated. Any that have prepared <hi>Vitriolum Martis,</hi> he hath learned this Note by it. Secondly, when the Vitrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Water doth ſettle its Colcothar without adding Gall to it, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways of a yellow Colour. This may be ſeen in the Stone Baſon and Spout of <hi>Knaisbrough Spaw,</hi> where the Water paſſing continually in the open air over it, hath precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated <hi>Crocus Martis,</hi> as I may call it thereupon. The like may be obſerved in every runner near the Fountain head of any Vitrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line or Chalybeate water whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. His Argument for Iron, <hi>pag.</hi> 14. <hi>The Earth that falls from the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64813:29"/>Bank turns to Iron-ſtone, as hard as Iron it ſelf, and fuſible being put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Smiths Forge, as I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times found upon tryal: There is a piece of the Cliff within one hundred paces of the</hi> Spaw, <hi>thus converted in a very ſew years to an Iron Stone, as much as would load three or four Carts:</hi> Anſwer, I here require the Smith to make Horſe-ſhoe Nails of it, and then I ſhall yield to Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> thus much, that within a hundred Paces of the <hi>Spaw</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward there is Iron-ſtone. To me it doth appear to be a reddiſh Earth diſſolved with the Nitroalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous Salt, and petrified in the Sun and Air to a hard lump, which will flux in the Fire, anſwerable to the Nature of that Salt that is in it. Another Argument for Iron (which for manners ſake I leave laſt) is that the <hi>Water colours the Excrements black:</hi> he ſhould have ſaid <hi>blew,</hi> for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64813:29"/>when he looks back again, they will appear of the ſame colour that Allom Stone is of. In his Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Simpſon,</hi> pag. 42. <hi>I knew</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Vitriol to be in the water from its eminent acidity.</hi> Anſwer. This is a <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> for acidity is appropriated to the Spirit of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, as well as to the Spirit of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol. <hi>Pag.</hi> 43. Another token of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol is, <hi>that Vitrioline vapour which any one of an indifferent ſmell may obſerve, which is ſomething likely of Ink, though more pure.</hi> Anſwer. Take this Experiment to know what ſmell <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> is of, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Take oily Water (after all the Chriſtals are ſettled from it mentioned before) exhaled per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly dry; adde hot water to it, then ſtir it, and if it do not ſtink as bad, or worſe than the Allom-pans at <hi>Whitby,</hi> I will forfeit my Noſe: why then ſays Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> 'tis a more
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64813:30"/>pure ſmell than that of Ink. <hi>Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis odor lucri ex re quâlibet.</hi> Pag. 44. <hi>Six ſcore paces from the</hi> Spring <hi>a</hi> Vitrioline Salt, <hi>of a dark yellow colour, ſweats out of the Cliff.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. The Nitre ſpires out of the Cliff all along Weſtward from the <hi>Spaw,</hi> of a white Colour, this he confeſſeth to be none other than Nitre; at a further diſtance it changeth Colour to a dark yellow, as the Earth doth out of which it ſweats: Let him hear <hi>Kircher</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming this truth, <hi>Capite de nitro; Quod ſi ſubindè nitrum variis colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus imbutum reperiatur, id nil tamèn diverſum à nitro, arguit cùm omnem colorem à colore terrae ex qua extractum fuit, trahat, ſi ex rubro, rubrum; ſi ab albo, album, &amp; ſic de caeteris, pag.</hi> 304. <hi>l.</hi> 6. Page 67. <hi>The black ſediment precipitated by the Gall, I Calcin'd</hi> (ſays Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>) <hi>and it became of a dark brown co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64813:30"/>and is none other than Scoria of Iron</hi> (he calcin'd likewiſe the whole Body of Minerals) <hi>and there are in it here and there flakes of Iron, broad and thin, like thoſe that flie off from the Smiths hammer.</hi> Anſwer. This calcin'd Sediment, and calcin'd Body are all one Experiment; for the Gall precipitates the groſs parts whatſoever they be: no marvel then if it became as hard as a Cinder, which had ſo much Stone in it as I have proved; for thoſe flakes of Iron that are diſcovered in the Body of Minerals, I confeſs I am not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious, I never yet undertook <hi>his method</hi> in ſearching what different parts were in this compound Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to calcine the whole Body of Minerals together, as that only expedient way; yet I <hi>calcin'd</hi> the <hi>Stone</hi> Powder, where moſt likely it ſhould be intermixed, and there they are not. I <hi>calcin'd</hi> alſo the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64813:31"/>
               <hi>Clay,</hi> neither are any <hi>Iron flakes</hi> there, wherefore it muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, like as he <hi>ſmelt</hi> the <hi>Vitriol,</hi> ſo he <hi>ſaw</hi> the <hi>Iron flakes, ideſt,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like them.</p>
            <p>The right improvement of this Water conſiſts in three indications.</p>
            <p>Firſt to reſiſt (if it were poſſible) the petrifying property; but this being to the Water <hi>proprium quarto nodo,</hi> ſmall help can be had againſt it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To hinder that the <hi>Stone</hi> Powder, and <hi>feces</hi> of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom fix not in the Bowels.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To prevent in tender conſtitutions that the duplicated Salt corrode not the Entrails, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereby a Dyſentery, which (ſays Dr. <hi>Witty, pag.</hi> 150.) rarely happens.</p>
            <p>All the harm that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is guilty of, proceeds from one of theſe cauſes.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:64813:31"/>
            <p>In his Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Simpſon,</hi> I read thus, <hi>pag.</hi> 238. <hi>And though Mr.</hi> Simpſon <hi>has deſign'd cauſleſly to rob me of the honour and reputation</hi> (if there be any in it) <hi>of my diſcovery of</hi> Scarbrough Spaw, <hi>with its uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to my Country, yet if he have any thing to make out in point of Art, I ſhall never go about to eclipſe it, but thank him to boot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he is a man of his word, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect thus much from him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
